<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

<!-- Include general documentation entities -->
<!ENTITY % docentities SYSTEM "../../../docbook/entities.xml">
%docentities;

]>
<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>
	
	<title>&adminguide;</title>
	
	<section>
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
		This module provides a generic database clustering system. It can be
		used as a middle layer between modules and database connectors.
	</para>
	<para>
		Via clustering, database operations can be executed across multiple
		servers, based on policies such as parallel write, serial or round
		robin write and read.
	</para>
	<para>
		The following database commands are considered to be write operations:
		INSERT, DELETE, UPDATE, REPLACE, INSERT-DELAYED, INSERT-UPDATE. The
		read operations are done for database commands: QUERY and RAW-QUERY.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>&kamailio; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>db connector</emphasis> - database connectors.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
		<para>
		The following libraries or applications must be installed before running
		&kamailio; with this module loaded:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>None</emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Parameters</title>
	<section id="db_cluster.p.connection">
		<title><varname>connection</varname> (str)</title>
		<para>
			Specify the connection to a real database system. The format is
			'conid=>DBURL' - providing a connection id and the database
			URL used by the database driver used.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is NULL.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>connection</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("db_cluster", "connection",
             "con1=>mysql://kamailio:kamailiorw@localhost/kamailio1")
modparam("db_cluster", "connection",
             "con2=>mysql://kamailio:kamailiorw@localhost/kamailio2")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="db_cluster.p.cluster">
		<title><varname>cluster</varname> (str)</title>
		<para>
			Specify the cluster definition. The format is
			'clsid=>conid1=def1;conid2=def2' - providing a cluster id and the list of
			database connections to be used. For each connection you have to provide
			a usage definition. The usage definition is a 4-char long string,
			specifying priority and command mode for read and write operations to be
			performed on that connection.
		</para>
		<para>
			The priority is a digit between 0 and 9, where a higher value means higher priority.
			Priority 0 means that the connection is not going to be used in that cluster.
		</para>
		<para>
			Command mode is a character among s, r and p. s is for doing serial
			operations (try first and if fails, try next); r is for doing round
			robin operations; p - is for doing parallel operations (this is valid
			only for write operations).
		</para>
		<para>
		<para>
			The first two characters is priority and mode for read, followed by
			two characters for priority and mode for write operations. "p" is 
			only used for write operations.
		</para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is NULL.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>cluster</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("db_cluster", "cluster", "cls1=>con1=9s8p;con2=9s8p")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="db_cluster.p.inactive_interval">
		<title><varname>inactive_interval</varname> (int)</title>
		<para>
			How long (seconds) a connection is considered inactive after a DB
			operations failed on it.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 300 (5 min).
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>inactive_interval</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("db_cluster", "inactive_interval", 180)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="db_cluster.p.max_query_length">
		<title><varname>max_query_length</varname> (int)</title>
		<para>
		How long (seconds) a failed db operation needs to last before
		deactivating the connection for inactive_interval seconds. This
		prevents disabling of connections that reply fast with error
		codes, thus being active (e.g., due to primary key insert errors).
		In such cases, the database server is active.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 0.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>max_query_length</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("db_cluster", "max_query_length", 5)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Usage</title>
		<para>
			Practically, all the modules that want to use a cluster, have to set
			their db_url parameter to "cluster://clusterid".
		</para>
		<para>
			Following rules apply when doing DB commands: the connecions with highest
			priority are chosen first and the operations are performed according
			to the command mode. Note that for same priority, only one command mode
			is used (the one from the first connection with that priority found
			in the definition of the cluster). If the DB command is not successful,
			next set of connections based on priority is selected and the command is
			tried again. When the command is successful, no other try is made.
		</para>
		<para>
			For parallel operations, a command is considered successful if it
			succeeded on one connection from a group with same priority.
		</para>
		<para>
			Next example shows how to set a cluster with two connections to MySQL
			to be used for parallel writing from acc and round-robin reading by
			sqlops.
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Sample of usage</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("db_cluster", "connection",
             "c1=&gt;mysql://kamailio:kamailiorw@localhost/kamailio1")
modparam("db_cluster", "connection",
             "c2=&gt;mysql://kamailio:kamailiorw@localhost/kamailio2")
modparam("db_cluster", "cluster", "k1=&gt;c1=9r9p;c2=9r9p")

modparam("acc", "db_url", "cluster://k1")

modparam("sqlops", "sqlcon", "ca=&gt;cluster://k1")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
</chapter>

