<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" 
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="lcr" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <sectioninfo>
	<authorgroup>
	    <author>
		<firstname>Juha</firstname>
		<surname>Heinanen</surname>
		<affiliation><orgname>FhG FOKUS</orgname></affiliation>
		<address>
		    <email></email>
		</address>
	    </author>
	</authorgroup>
	<copyright>
	    <year>2003</year>
	    <holder>FhG FOKUS</holder>
	</copyright>
	<revhistory>
	    <revision>
		<revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
		<date>$Date$</date>
	    </revision>
	</revhistory>
    </sectioninfo>

    <title>LCR Module</title>

    <section id="lcr.overview">
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
         Least cost routing (LCR) module implements two related capabilities:
       <itemizedlist>
            <listitem> LCR may sequentially forward requests to one or more gateways using the load_gws 
            and next_gw functions.
            </listitem>

            <listitem> LCR may sequentially forward contacts if they don't share the the same qvalues.
            Use the functions load_contacts and next_contacts to access and select a contact.
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

       <para>Gateway selection is based on caller's RPID URI (if available in caller's RPID AVP after 
        authentication) or From URI and user part of Request-URI (telephone number).  Gateway patterns
        matching RPID or From URI and telephone number are ordered for forwarding purposes as follows:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>According to longest user part match
            </listitem>

            <listitem>According to priority
            </listitem>

            <listitem>Randomly
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        Each gateway belongs to a gateway group either alone or among other gateways.  All gateways in a 
        group share the same priority.  Gateway and routing information is kept in two tables:  
        gw and lcr.
        </para>

        <para> When a gateway is selected, Request-URI is rewritten with information from gw table: 
         URI scheme, prefix, IP address, port, and transport protocol.  Valid URI scheme values are:
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>NULL = sip
            </listitem>
            <listitem>1 = sip 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>2 = sips.  
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para> If a prefix is specified it will be prepended to the Request-URI user part.
        </para>

        <para>Currently valid transport protocol values are: 
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>NULL = none
            </listitem>
            <listitem>1 = udp 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>2 = tcp  
            </listitem>
            <listitem>3 = tls  
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para> Table lcr contains any prefix to be applied to the user part of Request-URI, the From URI,
         the gateway group id, and the priority.  The From URI can contain special characters % and _ 
         matching any number of any characters and any one character, respectively. 
        </para>

        <para> In addition to gw and lcr tables there is third table gw_grp that is used for 
         administrative purposes only. In this table you may map names to the gateway group ids.
        </para>

	</para>
    </section>

    <section id="lcr.dependencies">
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<para>The module depends on the following modules. These modules must be loaded before the LCR module
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>tm module
            </listitem>
            <listitem>mysql module
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
	</para>
    </section>

    
    <xi:include href="params.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="functions.xml"/>

</section>

