<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" 
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="ser_rpc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <!--
    <sectioninfo>
        <releaseinfo role="cvs">$Revision$</releaseinfo>
        <pubdate role="cvs">$Date$</pubdate>
    </sectioninfo>
    -->
    
    <title>
	SER Management Interface
    </title>

    <section id="rpc.design">
	<title>Design Goals</title>
	<para>
	    
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
		<para>Implemented as a module.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>API independent of transport protocols.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>Reuse transports available in SER.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>The possibility to encrypt all communication.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>The possibility to authenticate clients.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>Easy integration with existing languages and
		    implementations.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Easy and straightforward implementation of management
		    functions in SER modules.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="rpc.overview">
	<title>Overview of Operation</title>
	<para>
	    The RPC (Remote Procedure Call) interface of SER is based on the
	    XML-RPC <ulink url="http://www.xmlrpc.com">de-facto
	    standard</ulink>. XML-RPC protocol encodes the name of the method
	    to be called along with its parameter in an XML document which is
	    then conveyed using HTTP (Hyper Text Transfer Protocol) to the
	    server. The server will extract the name of the function to be
	    called along with its parameters from the XML document, execute the
	    function, and encode any data returned by the function into another
	    XML document which is then returned to the client in the body of a
	    200 OK reply to the HTTP request.
	</para>
	<para>
	    XML-RPC is similar to more popular <ulink
		url="http://www.w3.org/TR/soap/">SOAP</ulink> (Simple Object
		Access Protocol), which is an XML-based messaging framework
		used in Web Services developed within the <ulink
		url="http://www.w3c.org">World Wide Web
		Consortium</ulink>. Both protocols are using HTTP as the
		transport protocol for XML documents, but XML-RPC is much
		simpler and easier to implement than SOAP.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Here is an example of single XML-RPC function call to determine
	    current time:
	</para>
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
POST /RPC2 HTTP/1.0
User-Agent: Radio UserLand/7.1b7 (WinNT)
Host: time.xmlrpc.com
Content-Type: text/xml
Content-length: 131
	    
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<methodCall>
<methodName>currentTime.getCurrentTime</methodName>
<params>
</params>
</methodCall>
]]>
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	    And the response returned by the server:
	</para>
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Connection: close
Content-Length: 183
Content-Type: text/xml
Date: Wed, 03 Oct 2001 15:53:38 GMT
Server: UserLand Frontier/7.0.1-WinNT

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<methodResponse>
<params>
<param>
<value><dateTime.iso8601>20011003T08:53:38</dateTime.iso8601>
</value>
</param>
</params>
</methodResponse>
]]>
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	    XML-RPC specification spells HTTP as the official transport
	    protocol for XML-RPC documents. SER does not directly support
	    HTTP, it is a SIP server so SIP is the only protocol supported by
	    SER. Because we would like to reuse all transport protocols
	    available in SER, such as TCP and TLS, it would be natural to use
	    modified version of XML-RPC which would run on top of SIP instead
	    of HTTP. XML-RPC documents would be then encoded in the bodies of
	    SIP requests and replies would be sent by the server in the bodies of
	    SIP replies. This way we could reuse all transport protocols
	    (including UDP) and message parsers available in SER.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Although this approach seems to be the logical choice, there is one
	    big drawback. No existing XML-RPC implementations support SIP as the
	    transport protocol, and there are many existing implementations
	    available for vast majority of existing languages. See the <ulink
	    url="http://www.xmlrpc.com/directory/1568/implementations">XML-RPC
	    implementation page</ulink> for more details. Extending existing
	    implementations with SIP support would not be easy.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Because  extending available XML-RPC implementation would be too
	    expensive, we could also do it the other way around, keep existing
	    XML-RPC implementations and extend SER to support HTTP. Extending
	    SER with HTTP support is easier than it might seem at a first
	    glance, due to the similarity between SIP requests and HTTP
	    requests.
	</para>
	<para>
	    SER already supports TCP, so existing HTTP implementations can send
	    HTTP requests to it. HTTP requests are missing certain mandatory
	    SIP header fields, such as Via, From, and CSeq. The contents of the
	    header fields is mainly used for transaction matching. A SIP server
	    could perform two basic operations when processing an HTTP
	    request:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Terminate the request, execute the function and send a
			reply back.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Forward the request to another SIP server.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	    Nothing special is needed on the SIP server terminating the
	    request, except that it has to know where it should send the
	    reply. Parsing of HTTP header field bodies would fail because we do
	    not have parsers for them in SER, but that does not matter anyway
	    because all the information is encoded in the body of the
	    request. HTTP requests contain no Via header fields. Via header
	    fields are used by SIP implementations to determine the destination
	    (IP, transport protocol, and port number) for replies. When
	    processing HTTP requests the SIP server needs to create a fake Via
	    header field based on the source IP address and port number of the
	    TCP connection. The SIP server will use this information when
	    sending a reply back.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Forwarding of HTTP requests by SIP proxies is a little bit more
	    complicated and there are several limitations. First of all, we can
	    only use stateless forwarding, no transactional forwarding, because
	    HTTP requests do not contain all the header fields needed for
	    transaction matching. Any attempt to call t_relay on an HTTP
	    requests would fail. HTTP requests always use TCP and thus we could
	    use stateless forwarding on the SIP server, provided that the
	    request will be also forwarded over TCP. Stateless forwarding does
	    not require the mandatory header fields (which are missing here)
	    and it would work. In addition to that, the SIP server would also
	    append fake Via header field to the request and change the contents
	    of the Request-URI. The Request-URI of HTTP requests sent by XML-RPC
	    implementations typically contain something like "/RPC2" and the
	    first SIP server processing the request should rewrite the value
	    with a valid SIP URI.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <xref linkend="fig.rpc_example"/> shows a scenario which involves
	    two SIP servers, one performs HTTP request "normalization" and
	    forwarding, and the other terminates the request, executes
	    corresponding function, and generates a reply.
	</para>
	<mediaobject id="fig.rpc_example" xreflabel="Figure RPC Example">
	    <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="rpc_example.png" format="PNG"/>
	    </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
		<para>Example RPC Scenario</para>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
		Example RPC Scenario
	    </caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 1.</emphasis> An HTTP user agent sends an ordinary
	    HTTP request to a SIP server. The user agent can either establish a
	    connection directly to port 5060 or the SIP server can be
	    configured to listen on port 80. The request contains standard HTTP
	    headers and an XML-RPC document in the body:
	    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
POST / HTTP/1.0.
Host: localhost:5060
User-Agent: xmlrpclib.py/1.0.1 (by www.pythonware.com)
Content-Type: text/xml
Content-Length: 111

<?xml version='1.0'?>
<methodCall>
<methodName>]]><emphasis>usrloc.statistics</emphasis><![CDATA[</methodName>
<params>
</params>
</methodCall>
]]>
	    </programlisting>
	    This particular request calls method "statistics" from from usrloc
	    module of SER. The method has no parameters.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The outbound SIP server receives the HTTP request and performs a
	    set of actions called "SIP-normalization". This includes creation
	    of fake Via header field based on the source IP and port of the TCP
	    connection, looking up of the target SIP server that should
	    terminate and process the request, and rewriting of the Request-URI
	    with the SIP URI of the target SIP server. Modified HTTP request
	    will be then forwarded statelessly to the target SIP server.
	    <programlisting>
POST <emphasis>sip:proxy01.sip-server.net</emphasis> HTTP/1.0
<emphasis>Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:3571</emphasis>
Host: localhost:5060
User-Agent: xmlrpclib.py/1.0.1 (by www.pythonware.com)
Content-Type: text/xml
Content-Length: 111
<![CDATA[
<?xml version='1.0'?>
<methodCall>
<methodName>usrloc.statistics</methodName>
<params>
</params>
</methodCall>
]]>
	    </programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 2.</emphasis> "normalized" HTTP request is
	    statelessly forwarded to the target SIP server over TCP.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 3.</emphasis> The target SIP server receives the
	    HTTP request and executes function called
	    <function>dispatch_rpc</function> from xmlrpc SER module. This
	    function will parse the XML-RPC document in the body of the request
	    and lookup the function to be called among all RPC functions
	    exported by the SER core and modules. Function
	    <function>dispatch_rpc</function> will be called from the
	    configuration file just like any other function:
	    <programlisting>
if (method == "POST" || method == "GET") {
    <emphasis>dispatch_rpc();</emphasis>
    break;
};
	    </programlisting>
	    This particular configuration snippet executes the function
	    whenever SER receives GET or POST requests. These two method names
	    indicate HTTP.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 4.</emphasis> Function
	    <function>dispatch_rpc</function> scans through the list of all
	    exported RPC functions searching for
	    <function>statistics</function> function of usrloc module. <xref
	    linkend="rpc.module_api"/> describes in detail how modules export
	    RPC functions.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 5.</emphasis> As the RPC function from usrloc module
	    is running and gathering statistics, it calls functions of RPC
	    interface to prepare the result for the caller.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Step 6.</emphasis> Once the RPC function finishes, xmlrpc
	    module will build the XML-RPC document from the data received from
	    usrloc module and generate a reply which will be sent to the caller.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Steps 7. and 8.</emphasis> HTTP reply is sent back to the
	    caller and the remote procedure call finishes.
	    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.0 200 OK
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:3571
Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))
Content-Length: 651
Warning: 392 127.0.0.1:5060 "Noisy feedback tells:  pid=9975 req_src_ip=127.0.0
1 req_src_port=3571 in_uri=/ out_uri=sip:proxy01.sip-server.net via_cnt==1"

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodResponse>
<params>
<param><value><array><data>
<value><struct>
<member><name>domain</name>
<value><string>aliases</string></value></member>
<member><name>users</name>
<value><i4>0</i4></value></member>
<member><name>expired</name>
<value><i4>0</i4></value></member>
</struct></value>
<value><struct>
<member><name>domain</name>
<value><string>location</string></value></member>
<member><name>users</name>
<value><i4>0</i4></value></member>
<member><name>expired</name>
<value><i4>0</i4></value></member>
</struct></value>
</data></array></value></param>
</params>
</methodResponse>
]]>
	    </programlisting>
	</para>
	<note>
	    <para>
		The scenario described on <xref linkend="fig.rpc_example"/>
		involves two SIP servers. This is just to demonstrate that in
		setups containing more SIP servers it is possible to forward
		HTTP requests from one SIP server to another and use standard
		SIP routing mechanisms to decide which SIP server should
		process the request. There is no need to have multiple SIP
		servers in simple setups, because one SIP server can both add 
		fake Via header field and process the RPC at the same
		time. Modified configuration file snipped could then look like
		this:
		<programlisting>
if (method == "POST" || method == "GET") {
    <emphasis>create_via();</emphasis>   # Create fake Via
    <emphasis>dispatch_rpc();</emphasis> # Process the request
    break;
};
		</programlisting>
	    </para>
	</note>
    </section>

    <section id="rpc.module_api">
	<title>Module API</title>
	<para>
	    Each SER module can export RPC functions just like it can export
	    parameters and functions to be called from the script. Whenever SER
	    receives an RPC request, it will search through the list of
	    exported RPC functions and the function with matching name will be
	    executed. A couple of essential RPC functions is also embedded into
	    the SER core.
	</para>
	<para>
	    This section gives a detailed overview of the whole RPC API. <xref
	    linkend="rpc.rpc_functions"/> describes the prototype and
	    conventions used in RPC functions. <xref linkend="rpc.data_types"/>
	    gives a detailed overview of available data types that can be used
	    in function parameters and return value. <xref
	    linkend="rpc.getting_parameters"/> describes functions of the RPC
	    API that can be used to retrieve parameters of the function, and
	    finally <xref linkend="rpc.creating_result"/> describes functions of
	    the API that can be used to build the result value that will be
	    sent in the reply to the caller.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The whole RPC API is described in header file
	    <filename>sip_router/rpc.h</filename>.  This file defines the set
	    of functions that must be implemented by RPC transport modules, as
	    described in <xref linkend="rpc.new_transport"/>, prototypes of RPC
	    functions and structures used for the communication between RPC
	    transport modules and ordinary modules exporting RPC functions.
	</para>
	<section id="rpc.rpc_functions">
	    <title>RPC Functions</title>
	    <para>
		RPC functions are standard C functions with the following
		prototype:
		<programlisting>
typedef void (*rpc_function_t)(rpc_t* rpc);
		</programlisting>
		RPC functions take one parameter, this parameter is a pointer
		to rpc_t structure and is called RPC context. The context
		contains references to all API functions available to the RPC
		function as well as all data necessary to create the
		response. RPC functions do not return any value, instead the
		return value is created using functions from the context. The
		motivation for this decision is the fact that RPC functions
		should always return a response and even the API functions
		called from RPC functions should have the possibility to
		indicate an error (and should not rely on RPC functions doing so).
	    </para>
	    <para>
		The RPC transport module creates initial reply before calling
		any RPC function. The default value of the reply is 200 OK with
		empty body. This is the value that will be returned to the
		caller and the function has to explicitly modify it if it wishes
		to either indicate a failure or add some data to the reply. The
		reply is sent automatically immediately after the RPC function
		finishes or the function can send the reply explicitly during
		its runtime. Even RPC API functions modify the reply upon a
		failure.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		Each RPC function has associated an array of documentation
		strings. The purpose of the documentation strings is to give a
		short overview of the function, accepted parameters, and format
		of the reply. By convention the name of the documentation string
		array is same as the name of the function with "_doc" suffix.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		Each module containing RPC functions has to export all the
		functions to SER core in order to make them visible to RPC
		transport modules. For this purpose, the
		<varname>module_exports</varname> structure of SER module API
		contains a new attribute called <varname>rpc_methods</varname>:
		<programlisting>
struct module_exports {
    char* name;                 /* null terminated module name */	
    cmd_export_t* cmds;         /* null terminated array of the exported commands */
    <emphasis>rpc_export_t* rpc_methods;</emphasis>  /* null terminated array of exported rpc methods */
    param_export_t* params;     /* null terminated array of the exported module parameters */
    
    init_function init_f;         /* Initialization function */
    response_function response_f; /* function used for responses */
    destroy_function destroy_f;   /* function called upon SER shutdown */
    onbreak_function onbreak_f;
    child_init_function init_child_f;  /* function called by all processes after the fork */
};

<emphasis>
typedef struct rpc_export {
    const char* name;        /* Name of the RPC function (null terminated) */
    rpc_function_t function; /* Pointer to the function */
    const char** doc_str;    /* Documentation strings, method signature and description */
    unsigned int flags;      /* Various flags, reserved for future use */
} rpc_export_t;
</emphasis>
		</programlisting>
		<varname>rpc_methods</varname> is pointer to an array of
		rpc_export_t structures. The last element of the array is a
		bumper containing zeroes in all attributes of the
		structure. The following program listing shows exported RPC
		functions of usrloc module: 
		<programlisting>
struct module_exports exports = {
    "usrloc",
    cmds,      /* Exported functions */ 
    <emphasis>ul_rpc</emphasis>,    /* RPC methods */
    params,    /* Export parameters */ 
    mod_init,  /* Module initialization function */ 
    0,         /* Response function */ 
    destroy,   /* Destroy function */ 
    0,         /* OnCancel function */ 
    child_init /* Child initialization function */ };

<emphasis>
rpc_export_t ul_rpc[] = {
    {"usrloc.statistics",      rpc_stats,           rpc_stats_doc,          0},
    {"usrloc.delete_aor",      rpc_delete_aor,      rpc_delete_aor_doc,     0},
    {"usrloc.delete_contact",  rpc_delete_contact,  rpc_delete_contact_doc, 0},
    {"usrloc.dump",            rpc_dump,            rpc_dump_doc,           0},
    {"usrloc.flush",           rpc_flush,           rpc_flush_doc,          0},
    {"usrloc.add_contact",     rpc_add_contact,     rpc_add_contact_doc,    0},
    {"usrloc.show_contacts",   rpc_show_contacts,   rpc_show_contacts_doc,  0},
    {0, 0, 0, 0}
};
</emphasis>
		</programlisting>
		By convention the name of every exported function consists of
		two parts delimited by a dot. The first part is the name of the
		module or SER subsystem this function belongs to. The second
		part is the name of the function. 
	    </para>
	    <para>
		Attribute <varname>flags</varname> of
		<varname>rpc_export</varname> structure is reserved for future
		use and is currently unused.
	    </para>
	</section>

	<section id="rpc.data_types">
	    <title>Data Types</title>
	    <para>
		The RPC API defines several basic and 1 compound data type
		that can be used in communication with the caller of RPC
		functions. The RPC API uses formating strings to describe data
		types. Each data type is described by exactly one character in
		the formating string. For example, if an RPC function calls
		function <function>add</function> of the RPC API and it passes
		two parameters to it, the first one of type string and the
		second one of type integer, the function parameters will look
		like:
		<programlisting>
add("sd", string_param, int_param);
		</programlisting>
		Character "s" in the formating string tells to the function
		that the 2nd parameter should be interpreted as string,
		character "d" in the formating string tells to the function
		that the 3rd parameter should be interpreted as signed integer.
	    </para>
	    <formalpara>
		<title>Integer</title>
		<para>
		    Integer type represents a signed 32-bit
		    integer. Corresponding character in the formating string is
		    "d". This parameter can be stored in C-style variable with
		    type <varname>int</varname>.
		</para>
	    </formalpara>
	    <formalpara>
		<title>Float</title>
		<para>
		    Float type represents a signed floating point
		    number. Corresponding character in the formating string is
		    "f". Data of this type can be stored in C-style variables
		    of type <varname>double</varname>.
		</para>
	    </formalpara>
	    <formalpara>
		<title>String</title>
		<para>
		    String type represents a string of characters. The string
		    may contain zeroes. This data type is represented by two
		    characters in the formatting string, either "s" or "S". "s"
		    indicates to the conversion function that the result should
		    be stored in a variable of type <varname>char*</varname>
		    and it should be zero terminated. "S" indicates to the
		    conversion function that the result will be stored in
		    a variable of type <varname>str</varname> which contains
		    both the pointer to the beginning of the string and its
		    length.
		</para>
	    </formalpara>
	    <formalpara>
		<title>Structure</title>
		<para>
		    Structure is the only compound data type currently defined
		    in the API. A structure is a collection of attributes. Each
		    attribute is identified using name (string) and each
		    attribute can be one of the basic data types, that
		    is integer, float, or string. Nesting of structures is not
		    allowed (in other words, structure attributes cannot be of
		    type struct again). Corresponding character in the
		    formatting string is "{". 
		</para>
	    </formalpara>
	    <table>
		<title>Data Type Overview</title>
		<tgroup cols="3">
		    <tbody>
			<row rowsep="1">
			    <entry>Name</entry>
			    <entry>Formating String Char</entry>
			    <entry>C-Style Variable</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
			    <entry>Integer</entry>
			    <entry>d</entry>
			    <entry>int</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
			    <entry>Float</entry>
			    <entry>f</entry>
			    <entry>double</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
			    <entry>String</entry>
			    <entry>s</entry>
			    <entry>char*</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
			    <entry>String</entry>
			    <entry>S</entry>
			    <entry>str</entry>
			</row>
		    </tbody>
		</tgroup>
	    </table>
	</section>

	<section id="rpc.getting_parameters">
	    <title>Getting Parameters</title>
	    <para>
		Each RPC function call can contain parameters. Parameters have
		no name, their meaning is determined by their position in the
		parameter set.
		<note>
		    <para>
			You can pass all parameters to a function within a
			structure if you want to make them position
			independent. Then each parameter can be retrieved by
			its name regardless of its position.
		    </para>
		</note>
		There are two functions in the RPC API that can be used to
		obtain function call parameters: <function>scan</function> and
		<function>struct_scan</function>.
	    </para>
	    <section id="rpc.scan">
		<title><function>scan</function></title>
		<para>
		    Function <function>scan</function> can be used to retrieve
		    parameters from the parameter set. The function accepts
		    variable number of parameters. The first parameter is the
		    formatting string that determines the type of the
		    parameters to be retrieved. Each parameter is represented by
		    exactly one character in the string. The variable part of
		    parameters must contain as many pointers to C variables as
		    there are formatting characters in the formatting
		    string.
		    <warning>
			<para>
			    The function will crash if you fail to provide
			    enough parameters.
			</para>
		    </warning>
		    The function indicates success by returning 0. When a
		    failure occurs (incorrect parameter type or no more
		    parameters in the parameter set) then the function will
		    return -1 and it will also automatically change the reply
		    that will be sent to the caller to indicate that a failure
		    has occurred on the server. Prototype of the function is:
		    <programlisting>
int scan(char* fmt, ...)
		    </programlisting>
		    It is possible to either call the function once to scan all
		    the parameters:
		    <programlisting>
rpc->scan("sdf", &amp;string_val, &amp;int_val, &amp;double_val);
		    </programlisting>
		    Or you can call the same function several times and it will
		    continue where it left off previously:
		    <programlisting>
rpc->scan("s", &amp;string_val);
rpc->scan("d", &amp;int_val);
rpc->scan("f", &amp;double_val);
		    </programlisting>
		</para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
		<title><function>struct_scan</function></title>
		<para>
		    Function <function>struct_scan</function> can be used to
		    retrieve named attributes from a parameter of type
		    structure. When retrieving a structure parameter from the
		    parameter set:
		    <programlisting>
rpc->scan("{", &amp;handle);
		    </programlisting>
		    The corresponding variable (named 
		    <varname>handle</varname>in the example above) will contain
		    the index of the structure parameter within the parameter
		    set, but the index cannot be used to retrieve the contents
		    of the structure. To retrieve the contents of the structure
		    you can use function <function>struct_scan</function>. The
		    function gets the handle as the first parameter:
		    <programlisting>
rpc->struct_scan(handle, "sd", "str_attr", &amp;str_val, "int_attr", &amp;int_val);
		    </programlisting>
		    The second parameter is the formatting string followed by
		    pairs of parameters. First parameter in each pair is the
		    name of the attribute to retrieve (string) and the second
		    parameter in each pair is the pointer to the variable to
		    store the value of the parameter. The function returns 0 on
		    success and -1 on an error (just like
		    <function>scan</function> function). The function also
		    indicates an error if a requested attribute is missing in
		    the structure.
		</para>
	    </section>

	    <example>
		<title>Retrieving Parameters</title>
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_delete_contact(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    str aor, contact;
    char* table;
    int handle, expires;
    double q;

    if (rpc->scan("sS{", &table, &aor, &handle) < 0) {
        /* Reply is set automatically by scan upon failure,
         * no need to do anything here
         */
        return;
    }

    if (rpc->struct_scan(handle, "Sdf", &contact, &expires, &q) < 0) {
        /* Reply is set automatically by struct_scan upon failure,
         * no need to do anything here
         */
        return;
    }

    /* Process retrieved parameters here */
}
]]>
		</programlisting>
	    </example>
	</section>

	<section id="rpc.creating_result">
	    <title>Building Reply</title>
	    <para>
		The RPC API contains several functions that can be used to
		modify and/or send a reply. The functions use formatting
		strings and parameter lists just like functions described in
		<xref linkend="rpc.getting_parameters"/>.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		Each RPC function call must return a reply. The reply can be
		either a failure reply or success reply. Failure replies
		contain only the status code and reason phrase. Success
		replies can have arbitrary amount of data attached to
		them. Status codes 3xx, 4xx, 5xx, and 6xx indicate
		failures. Status code 2xx indicates success.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		The default reply is 200 OK with no data attached to it. This
		is what will be returned by the RPC transport module if you do
		not call any of the reply-related functions described in this
		section.
		<example>
		    <title>Sending default reply</title>
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_dummy(rpc_t* rpc)
{
  /* 200 OK with no data will be returned */
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		</example>
	    </para>
	    <section>
		<title>fault</title>
		<para>
		    You can use <function>fault</function> function to indicate
		    that an error has occurred on the server to the caller. The
		    function accepts two parameters. The first parameter is the
		    status code and the second parameter is the reason phrase.
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_my_function(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    rpc->fault(600, "Not Yet Implemented");
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		    If your function first creates some result using
		    <function>add</function>, or <function>printf</function>
		    functions then all the data will be lost once you call
		    <function>fault</function> function. Failure replies must
		    not contain any data:
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_my_function(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    rpc->add("s", "result1");
    rpc->add("d", variable);

    /* Reply created by previous functions will be
     * deleted and a failure reply 600 Not Yet Implemented
     * will be created instead
     */
    rpc->fault(600, "Not Yet Implemented");

    /* You can also add data here, but that will have no
     * effect
     */
    rpc->add("s", "result2");
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		    Similarly you can also call <function>add</function> or
		    <function>printf</function> functions after calling
		    <function>fault</function>, in this case they will have no
		    effect:
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_my_function(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    rpc->fault(600, "Not Yet Implemented");

    /* You can also add data here, but that will have no
     * effect and only 600 Not Yet Implemented will be returned
     */
    rpc->add("s", "result2");
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		</para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
		<title>send</title>
		<para>
		    RPC functions can use function <function>send</function> to
		    explicitly send the reply. Each RPC function call generates
		    exactly one reply. No reply will be sent after the function
		    finishes if it already sent the reply using
		    <function>send</function> function explicitly. This
		    function is especially useful if the RPC function needs to
		    perform some (potentially destructive) actions after the
		    reply has been sent.
		</para>
		<example>
		    <title>Kill the server</title>
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void core_kill(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    int sig_no;

    if (rpc->scan("d", &sig_no) < 0) return;
    rpc->send();     /* First send a reply */
    kill(0, sig_no); /* Then kill the server */
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		</example>
		
	    </section>
	    <section>
		<title>add</title>
		<para>
		    Function <function>add</function> can be used to add
		    arbitrary data to the result set. Its parameters and use
		    are analogical to <function>scan</function> function
		    described in <xref linkend="rpc.scan"/>. The first
		    parameter of the function is the formatting string that
		    determines the types of additional parameters:
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_func(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    str str_result;
    int int_result, handle;
    double float_result;

    if (rpc->add("Sdf{", &str_result, int_result, float_result, &handle) < 0) return;
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		    Naturally you can call this function several times, adding
		    only one piece of data at a time. The function returns 0 on
		    success and -1 on an error. In case of an error the reply
		    is set automatically with corresponding error code and
		    reason phrase.
		</para>
		<para>
		    The last character in the formatting string of the function
		    above indicates that the last data to be added will be a
		    structure. This deserves some clarification. In this case,
		    the function will create an empty structure and the handle
		    to the newly created structure will be stored in
		    <varname>handle</varname> variable (hence the last
		    parameter is pointer to an integer). In this particular
		    example parameters <varname>str_result</varname>,
		    <varname>int_result</varname>, and
		    <varname>float_result</varname> will be used for reading
		    while parameter <varname>handle</varname> will be used for
		    writing by the function.
		</para>
		<para>
		    You can set the attributes of the newly created structure
		    using <function>struct_add</function> function described in
		    <xref linkend="rpc.struct_add"/>.
		</para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
		<title>printf</title>
		<para>
		    <varname>printf</varname> is a convenience function. The
		    function adds data of type string to the result set. The
		    first parameter of the function is again a formatting
		    string, but this time it is <function>printf</function>-like formatting string:
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
if (rpc->printf("Unable to delete %d entries from table %s", num_entries, table_name) < 0) return;
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		    The return value of the function is the same as of
		    <function>add</function> function.
		</para>
	    </section>
	    <section id="rpc.struct_add">
		<title>struct_add</title>
		<para>
		    Function <function>struct_add</function> can be used to add
		    attributes to a structure (created previously by
		    <function>add</function> function). The first parameter of
		    the function is handle obtained through
		    <function>add</function> function, the second parameters is
		    formatting string that determines the types of attributes
		    to be added. There must be two parameters per each
		    character in the formatting string, the first one is the
		    name of the attribute, the second parameter is the value
		    of the attribute. If a parameter with such a name already
		    exist in the structure then it will be overwritten with the
		    new value.
		    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_func(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    int handle;

      /* Create empty structure and obtain its handle */
    if (rpc->add("{", &handle) < 0) return;
      /* Fill-in the structure */
    if (rpc->struct_add(handle, "sd", "attr1", str_val, "attr2", int_val) < 0) return;
}
]]>
		    </programlisting>
		    The function returns -1 on an error (and sets the status
		    code and reason phrase of the reply accordingly) and 0 on success.
		</para>
	    </section>
	</section>

	<section>
	    <title>Real World Example</title>
	    <para>
		The following example illustrates the use of most of the
		functions from the API together:
	    </para>
	    <example>
		<title>Real World Example RPC Function</title>
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
static void rpc_register(rpc_t* rpc)
{
    char* domain;
    str aor;
    contact_t contact, new_contact;
    int handle;

        /* Extract the domain, address of record from the request */
    if (rpc->scan("sS{", &domain, &aor, &handle) < 0) return;
        /* Extract the structure describing the contact to be processed */
    if (rpc->struct_scan(handle, "Sdf", &contact.c, &contact.expires, &contact.q) < 0) return;

        /* Process the contact, new_contact will contain updated value after processing */
    if (process_contact(domain, &aor, &new_contact, &contact) < 0) {
           /* Processing failed, indicate the failure to the caller */
        rpc->fault(500, "Error While Processing Contact");
        return;
    }

        /* Return the domain and the address of record */
    rpc->add("sS{", &domain, &aor, &handle) < 0) return;
        /* And also add the new values for contact, q, and expires parameters */
    rpc->struct_add(handle, "Sdf", &new_contact.c, &new_contact.expires, &new_contact.q);
}
]]>
		</programlisting>
	    </example>
	</section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="rpc.xmlrpc">
	<title>XML-RPC Transport</title>
	<para>
	    The XML-RPC transport is implemented in xmlrpc SER module. The
	    purpose of the functions of the module is to convert XML-RPC
	    document carried in the body of HTTP requests into data returned by
	    the RPC interface and back. The module also contains functions
	    necessary to "normalize" HTTP requests. The module uses <ulink
		url="http://xmlrpc-c.sourceforge.net">xmlrpc-c</ulink>
	    library to perform XML-RPC related functions.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The module always returns 200 OK HTTP reply, it will never return
	    any other HTTP reply. Failures are expressed in XML-RPC documents
	    in the body of the reply. There is basic method introspection
	    support in the module. Currently the module can list all functions
	    exported by the server and for each function it can return the
	    documentation string describing the function.
	</para>
	<section>
	    <title>Requests</title>
	    <para>
		Requests processed by the module are standard XML-RPC requests
		encoded in bodies of HTTP requests.
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
POST / HTTP/1.0
Host: localhost:5060
User-Agent: xmlrpclib.py/1.0.1 (by www.pythonware.com)
Content-Type: text/xml
Content-Length: 112

<?xml version='1.0'?>
<methodCall>
]]><emphasis><![CDATA[<methodName>system.listMethods</methodName>]]></emphasis><![CDATA[
<params>
</params>
</methodCall>
]]>
		</programlisting>
		The name of the method to be called in this example is
		"listMethods". This is one of the introspection methods. SER
		will call <function>dispatch_rpc</function> function of xmlrpc
		module to handle the request. The function will parse the
		XML-RPC document, lookup <function>listMethods</function>
		function in the list of all export RPC functions, prepare the
		context for the function and execute it.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Replies</title>
	    <para>
		The module will always generate 200 OK. Other response codes
		and classes are reserved for SER. The status code of the
		XML-RPC reply, response code, and additional data will be
		encoded in the body of the reply. Failure replies do not
		contain any data, just the response code and reason phrase:
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.0 200 OK
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:2464
Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))
Content-Length: 301

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodResponse>
]]><emphasis><![CDATA[
<fault>
<value><struct>
<member><name>faultCode</name>
<value><i4>501</i4></value></member>
<member><name>faultString</name>
<value><string>Method Not Implemented</string></value></member>
</struct></value>
</fault>
]]></emphasis><![CDATA[
</methodResponse>
]]>
		</programlisting>
		This particular reply indicates that there is no such RPC
		method available on the server.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		Success replies always contain at least one return value. In
		our case the simplest success replies contain single boolean
		with value 1:
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.0 200 OK
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:4626
Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))
Content-Length: 150

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodResponse>
<params>
]]><emphasis><![CDATA[<param><value><boolean>1</boolean></value></param>]]></emphasis><![CDATA[
</params>
</methodResponse>
]]>
		</programlisting>
		This is exactly how the reply looks like when an RPC function
		does not add any data to the reply set.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		If an RPC function adds just a single item (it calls
		<function>add</function> once
		with just one character in the formatting string) then the data
		will be converted to XML-RPC representation according to the
		rules described in <xref linkend="rpc.type_conversion"/> and
		the reply will contain just the single value:
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.0 200 OK
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:3793
Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))
Content-Length: 216

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodResponse>
<params>
]]><emphasis><![CDATA[<param><value><string>Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))</string></value></param>]]></emphasis><![CDATA[
</params>
</methodResponse>
]]>
		</programlisting>
	    </para>
	    <para>
		If an RPC function adds more than one data items to the result
		set then the module will return an array containing all the
		data items:
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
HTTP/1.0 200 OK
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 127.0.0.1:2932
Server: Sip EXpress router (0.10.99-janakj_experimental (i386/linux))
Content-Length: 276

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodResponse>
<params>
<param><value>]]><emphasis><![CDATA[<array><data>
<value><string>./ser</string></value>
<value><string>-f</string></value>
<value><string>ser.cfg</string></value>
</data></array>]]></emphasis><![CDATA[</value></param>
</params>
</methodResponse>
]]>
		</programlisting>
		This is probably the most common scenario.
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section id="rpc.type_conversion">
	    <title>Type Conversion</title>
	    <para>
		The data types of the RPC API are converted to the data types
		of XML-RPC and vice versa. <xref
		linkend="tab.type_conversion"/> shows for each RPC API data
		type corresponding XML-RPC data type.
		<table id="tab.type_conversion">
		    <title>Data Type Conversion</title>
		    <tgroup cols="3">
			<tbody>
			    <row>
				<entry>RPC API</entry>
				<entry>XML-RPC</entry>
				<entry>RPC Example</entry>
				<entry>XML-RPC Example</entry>
			    </row>
			    <row>
				<entry>Integer</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<i4></i4>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
				<entry>rpc->add("d", 42)</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<i4>42</i4>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
			    </row>
			    <row>
				<entry>Float</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<double></double>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
				<entry>rpc->add("f", -12.214)</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<double>-12.214</double>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
			    </row>
			    <row>
				<entry>String</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<string></string>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
				<entry>rpc->add("s","Don't panic")</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<string>Don't panic</string>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
			    </row>
			    <row>
				<entry>Struct</entry>
				<entry>
				    <markup role="xmlrpc">
					<![CDATA[
					<struct></struct>
					]]>
				    </markup>
				</entry>
				<entry>rpc->struct_add(handle,"sd","param1",42,"param2",-12.214)</entry>
				<entry>
				    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<struct>
  <member>
    <name>param1</name>
    <value>
      <i4>42</i4>
    </value>
  </member>
  <member>
    <name>param2</name>
    <value>
      <double>-12.214</i4>
    </value>
  </member>
</struct>
]]>
				    </programlisting>
				</entry>
			    </row>
			</tbody>
		    </tgroup>
		</table>
	    </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	    <title>Limitations</title>
	    <para>
		SER xmlrpc modules does not implement all data types allowed in
		XML-RPC. As well it does not implement arrays and nested
		structures. This simplification is a feature, not bug. In our
		case the XML-RPC interface will be used mainly for management
		purposes and we do not need all the bells and whistles of
		XML-RPC. Parsing and interpreting nested structures is
		complex and we try to avoid it.
	    </para>
	</section>
    </section>

    <section>
	<title>Client Examples</title>
	To be done.
	<!--
	    implement clients in various languages 
	- pros, cons 
	- How failures
	    are mapped to XMLRPC 
	- How success replies are mapped 
	- How data
	    types of the API are mapped to XMLRPC elements 
	- 200 OK with no
	    data transformed to one value - True
	-->
    </section>

    <section id="rpc.new_transport">
	<title>Implementing New Transports</title>
	To be done.
	<!--
	- create a new module
	- take a look at sip_router/rpc.h
	- implement all functions in that header field
	- no garbage collection in rpc functions, the module needs to keep
	track of all allocated data
	- return value default to true
	- parameter type conflict is an error
	- missing struct attribute is an error
	- always send a reply, prepare replies so that you do not have to
	allocate memory at runtime
	- str strings do not have to be zero terminated
	- no structure/array nesting allowed
	- printf creates string attribute
        -->
    </section>
</section>
